Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太と
ひびと
栄光の日 生まれの弟･日々人＞
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
Born under a lucky star, younger brother Hibito becomes the first Japanese moonwalker.
＜日本人初の
ﾑｰﾝｳｫｰｶｰとなった日々人は➡
To treat the panic disorder that's afflicted him since a lunar accident, Hibito went to Russia.
月面での事故の影響による
パニック障害を克服するため➡
リハビリの日々を送る｡
一方 日々人のはるか後ろから➡
But now, Mutta is finally one step closer to the moon.
月を目指し始めた六太は
ついに新たな一歩を踏み出す＞
During NEEMO training, he will live in the environment closest to that of the moon,
ニーモ
＜ＮＥＥＭＯ訓練｡地球上で最も
月面を再現できる海底基地で➡
within a simulated lunar habitat.
シミュレーション生活を
するというもの＞
For this training, his life will be in real danger.
＜死の危険も伴う
油断できない訓練＞
In the coming days, Mutta and the other astronauts will face difficult trials.
＜六太たちに
重い試練がのしかかる！＞
Swayed by a profound sadness
My daydreams lay a bouquet at my feet
space brothers
I stand atop a brand new world
Hoping to catch whatever falls out of this unprecedented miracle
They're here yet again
The days I'll spend growing distant from you
I'll have miles to go before I sleep in peace
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It got mixed into your blood one day and hasn't let you go
That's all
My body grows nimbler by the day
And my heart's shedding tears because it can't keep up
But I lost something once I became an adult
My light slumber
I can see the faint radiance of hope
It's mixed into your blood, so I'll never let you go
That's all
My body stands atop a stage that it won't run away from even if it rains
That makes me break out into a sprint, so goodbye
My midnight slumbers
#82 Space Family
(せりか)《そろそろかな～》
It's almost time...
なぁに せりか
時計ばっかり見て｡
Why do you keep checking the clock, Serika?
もうランチが待ち遠しいの？
Can't wait for lunch?
ちっ 違う違う｡
Th-That isn't it.
えな
絵名ちゃんがね 今頃…｡
Ena's about to...
日本人というのは やはり➡
It appears that Japanese astronauts are better with their hands.
我々より器用というか
繊細な作業に長けているようだね｡
Especially when it comes to delicate work.
あ そうかもしれないですね｡
Oh, I suppose so.
People usually tell me that I'm more delicate than I appear.
おおざっぱ
私は 大雑把なタイプに
見られがちですけど➡
｢実は繊細なんだね｣って
よく言われます｡
《う～ん
そういう事じゃなくて…》
That wasn't what I meant...
ゴホン｡
まあ 君のね
ロボットアームの技量に関して➡
In any case,
I've received your instructors' report regarding your ability with the robotic arm.
指導員から
審査の報告があってね｡➡
｢繊細な作業も正確かつ
スピーディーにこなす腕前だ｡➡
You were able to perform accurate movements in a timely fashion.
そして ここ数年で間違いなく➡
And it's been years since they've seen anyone with your instincts.
一番センスがいい｣
という話だったよ｡
(ﾊﾞﾄﾗｰの声)ぜひその能力を…｡
We want you to put those skills to use...
Serika!
(北村)せりかちゃん！
やったよ！
I'm in!
ＩＳＳで生かしてほしい｡
...on the ISS.
I was chosen for the next ISS crew, as well!
私も 次のＩＳＳサブクルーに
選ばれたよ！
Congrats!
おめでと～！
素晴らしい！
さすがエナだ｡
Marvelous!
Way to go, Ena!
よかったね！
That's great!
いつも ひとり残って➡
Staying behind to practice on the robotic arm paid off!
ロボットアームの練習
してたもんね｡
What? You knew about that?
えっ 知ってたの？
Yep.
今夜はお祝いに
おいしいもの食べに行こうね｡
To celebrate, we should grab something to eat.
もうお店 予約してあるから｡
I already made a reservation.
(北村)は 早い…
さすが せりかちゃん｡
Th-That was fast...
I should have known.
We will now explain the task that you will spend eleven of the next twelve days performing.
これから 最終日を除く１２日間で
やってもらう 課題を説明する｡
各自 メールを見てくれ｡
Please check your e-mail.
There are three teams, on Aquarius I, II, and III.
アクエリアス ワン ツー スリーの
３チーム｡➡
Each team will be asked to construct a 1/3 scale model of Moonbase and the surrounding facilities.
それぞれ ３分の１スケールの
月面基地➡
及び 周辺設備のモデルを
船外に建設すること｡➡
骨組みだけの
簡易的なつくりで構わない｡➡
You only need to set up the framework.
ずいじ
素材は こちらで随時 海に
沈めていくものを使用してくれ｡➡
We will drop necessary materials into the water.
各チームの新人２人が➡
On each team, the two rookies will come up with ideas for the surrounding facilities.
基地の設備などの
アイデアを出し合い➡
先輩２人が採用案を
検討するものとする｡➡
While the veterans will decide which ideas to use.
｢設計･建設作業｣の
役割分担等については➡
We will let each team determine who is assigned to the design and construction phases.
各チームの方針に委ねる｡
その他 詳細はメールの説明文を
読んでくれ｡以上｡
Further instructions can be found in the e-mail.
That will be all.
なんば
な なるほど ミニ月面基地か｡
I see...
A miniature Moonbase...
でも１２日間じゃ
キツすぎねぇか？
Still, twelve days isn't much time.
This must be the training you mentioned that will require teamwork.
これがラブさんが言ってた
チーム戦になるっていう訓練？
まあな 実際
そうじゃなかったとしても➡
Probably.
Even if it isn't their intent, that's how I'm approaching the exercise.
俺らはそのつもりでいく｡
(パキ パキ…)
お前らの腕の見せ所だぜ
｢アンツ｣｡➡
Time to see what you can do, Ants.
しっかりアピールするんだな｡
Make sure you show off your skills.
時間がない
早く始めよう ムッ君！
おう！
We have no time... Let's get started, Mu.
Yeah.
課題の説明文には
｢コストは気にせず➡
The instructions say we don't need to worry about cost when we propose ideas.
自由に発想せよ｣って
書いてあるんだけど｡
あるね｡
True...
自由に新たな月面基地を作るのか
それとも➡
We can make up a brand-new Moonbase
or expand upon its current design.
今 実在している月面基地を
発展させる方向でいくか｡
ムッ君はどっちがいい？
時間食いそうだけど 俺は…｡
What's your preference, Mu?
It'll take longer, but I'd choose the former.
後者で｡
一緒だ｡
I agree.
将来的に 実現可能な範囲で
やりたいよね｡➡
We want to use a design that could be realized in the near future.
きっと その方が
評価は高いと思うんだ｡
I'd guess that will be better received.
Yeah.
Try not to play it too safe and give us something boring.
無難路線で つまらんものに
しねぇでくれよ｡
That's done, then. Next.
よし 決定｡で 次…｡
We're supposed to build a miniature model, to see how the finished product will look.
本来ならここで 完成予想として
ﾐﾆﾁｭｱを作るべきなんだろうけど｡
この手順を踏むかどうか｡
But is it worth the effort?
We're already building a 1/3 scale model.
船外に作る基地も
３分の１の模型だしな｡
模型のための模型は
省いていいんじゃねぇか？
I think it makes sense to skip building a model of a model.
ハッハハ 確かに｡
じゃあとりあえず➡
True.
Then let's download the current Moonbase's blueprints.
今ある基地の図面を
ダウンロードしておこう｡
《やっぱり…➡
I knew it...
やっぱりケンジとのコンビは
やりやすいぜ》
It's a lot easier working with Kenji.
《どんどん進めてくれるし
サクサク決まっていく》
He moves quickly, and makes decisions without hesitation.
《このコンビで月に行けたら
楽～しいだろうなぁ》
If we can go to the moon together,
it'll be a lot of fun...
(ｼｪｲﾝ)逆だよ ニッタ！➡
You've got it backward, Nitta!
時間がないからこそ
自由にいかなきゃ！
We don't have time, so we should think big.
この一文 読んだ？
Did you read this sentence?
It says not to worry about budget.
｢コストは気にせず
自由に発想せよ｣｡ねっ！
See? We should build something more fun!
もっと楽しいもの
作っちゃっていいんだよ｡
What are you thinking of?
じゃあ どうする？月面に
メリーゴーラウンドでも作るか？
Want to put a carousel on the moon?
アッハハ ニッタ
いいじゃん それ｡
Nitta, that's a good idea!
でも もっと
未来を見てこうぜ｡
But now, let's consider the future.
俺なら｢火星へ行くロケットと
射台｣は外せないね｡➡
I'd insist on a launchpad, for sending a rocket to Mars.
月からの打ち上げは低重力の分
地球からより２割削減でいける｡
Since the moon has less gravity, the rocket could be twenty percent less powerful.
あと 未来じゃ
月での長距離移動には➡
And in the future, we'll probably use planes to move around the Moon,
飛行機を使うように
なってるだろうから➡
空港が出来てるはずだ｡
リニア式の滑走路も作ろう｡
so we'll need airports.
We also want linear runways.
そんな大掛かりな
未来予想図みたいでいいのかよ｡
Are you serious about going with a futuristic Moonbase idea?
いやいや ニッタ｡➡
Hold on, Nitta.
俺たちは未来に
大きなビジョンを持つ必要がある｡
When it comes to the moon, we should be visionaries.
アポロ時代の再来だ｡➡
It'll be the Apollo era all over again.
大きなことを言い切らねぇと
大きな事は実現できない｡
To enact big things, you have to talk big.
大容量 通信アンテナも
ほしいね｡
We'll want a high-capacity communication antenna.
高画質の映像データを
地上に送信するためにね｡
That way, they can send high-quality video from the moon to Earth.
Oh, I like the sound of that.
おお いいねぇ！
Anything you want, Mu?
(ケンジ)ムッ君は何がほしい？
そうだな 俺は…｡
Oh, well...
ローバーとかビートルのさ➡
I'd be interested in charging stations for Beetle and the rover.
充電ポストは
そこいらにあってほしいな｡
基地から離れた場所でも
充電できれば活動範囲も広がるし｡
If we can charge vehicles away from the base, we can travel farther.
何より もしもの時
すぐに出動できるよ｡
And we can respond faster in case of emergency.
⦅ああっ！ぐわぁ！⦆
⦅ハァ ハァ ハァ…！⦆
そうだね 一刻を争うって時に
往復分の充電時間は➡
You're right.
In times of crisis,
we can't wait for a vehicle to return to base for recharging.
長くて待ってられないよね｡
あとさ…｡
Also...
If there's time, I'd like to try one thing.
なんとか時間作ってでも 個人的に
挑戦したいものがあんだけど…｡
いいかな？
いいよいいよ まずは
どんどん案を出していこう｡
Is that okay?
Sure... Right now, our goal is to brainstorm.
⦅我々は今
有力視しているのは 月面…➡
The most probable scenario on the moon would be a radio telescope.
電波望遠鏡です｡➡
つまり この案は 月に望遠鏡を
送り込むのではなく➡
In other words, we do not propose to transport a telescope to the moon.
月で望遠鏡を作ってしまう⦆
Our proposal is to construct the telescope there.
月面望遠鏡｡
A lunar telescope.
(ﾊﾐﾙﾄﾝ)ワァオ！
ロマンチックだね～｡
Wow, that's romantic...
Is there such a thing?
いるか？そんなもん｡
どんなもんか俺もまだ
よくわかってないけど➡
I'm not entirely sure how it's meant to work,
予習しときたいんだよ｡
but I want to get some practice.
いいね すごくいいと思うよ｡
I like it... I think it's a great idea!
Practice, huh?
予習かぁ 僕も月で自分がやる事を
前提に考えないとなぁ｡
I guess I should consider what I'll be doing on the moon.
一緒にやろうぜ 望遠鏡も｡
We can build the telescope together.
(ラブ)ハッ まったく➡
Heh, you guys are too naïve.
おめでたい奴らだな お前らは｡
お前ら ２人揃って
月に行けるとでも思ってんのか？
You actually think you'll get to go to the moon together?
Huh?
わかってねぇな…｡
(ｱﾝﾃﾞｨ)おい ラブ！
Not a clue...
Hey, Love!
(ｱﾝﾃﾞｨ)やめとけ…｡
Stop.
Hey, Daddy...
パパ 月 行くの？
Are you going to the moon?
そうだね きっと行くよ｡
そのための訓練も始まったしね｡
Yes, I'm sure I'll get there.
It's what I'm training for right now.
Oh...
(ユキ)ホント 信じられないよね｡
Yep, hard to believe, isn't it?
ウチのパパが月に行くなんて｡
Your daddy's going to the moon.
すごいねぇ～
パパ すご～い！
That's amazing... Daddy's amazing!
《アスキャンの
訓練が始まってから…》
After we began training as AsCans,
《４ヶ月が過ぎた頃…》
four months passed...
(ユキ)久しぶり！
It's been too long!
ほら｡
Come on!
(ケンジ)《待ちわびた再会｡➡
...before we were finally reunited.
家族とヒューストンでの生活が
始まった》
That was when our family started life in Houston.
あっ 来た！
フーちゃん ホラ！
Oh, there he is! Look, Fu!
うわぁ～！
Wow!
パパ 速い～！
Daddy's so fast!
《覚悟していた以上に 暮らしは
ガラリと変わってしまった》
I was expecting a lifestyle change, but it was even worse than that.
行ってくるよ｡
今度は１２日間だ｡
I'm off, then.
This time, I'll be gone twelve days.
Don't go!
やぁ～だ～！
いやぁ～！
Don't go!
(風佳)やだったら やだぁ～！
おい 風佳…｡
I don't want you to go!
Come on, Fuuka...
I spent five days in France for an international conference.
《フランスで国際会議と
視察５日間➡
カナダでロボットアームや➡
Seven days in Canada, training to operate robotic arms and other equipment.
実験装置の操作方法などの
訓練７日間…｡➡
かと思えば
日本の筑波に５日間戻ったり➡
Then five days back at Tsukuba, in Japan.
Space and Family - Makabe Kenji
ロシアでの雪上ｻﾊﾞｲﾊﾞﾙ訓練のために
７日間滞在したり➡
And in Russia for seven days, for survival training in the snow.
家族と会えない時間が
ようしゃ
容赦なく増えた…》
I was losing a lot of family time.
ﾏｲ ﾁｬｲﾙﾄﾞ ｲｽﾞ ﾐｯｼﾝｸﾞ｡
My child is missing.
ﾌﾟﾘｰｽﾞ ﾍﾙﾌﾟﾐｰ ﾌｧｲﾝﾄﾞ ﾊｰ｡
Please help me find her.
アゲイン
[PC]again.
Again.
My child is missing.
ﾏｲ ﾁｬｲﾙﾄﾞ ｲｽﾞ ﾐｯｼﾝｸﾞ｡➡
ﾌﾟﾘｰｽﾞ ﾍﾙﾌﾟﾐｰ ﾌｧｲﾝﾄﾞ ﾊｰ｡
Please help me find her.
あ～ またこんなに散らかして～！
Why do you have to make such a mess?
Honestly...
(風佳)はぁ…はぁ…｡
大丈夫？歩ける？
Are you okay? Can you walk?
ハウ
ロング
ハブ
ハッド
フィーバー
How long have she had a fever？
How long has she had a fever?
《どうしよ…
ほとんど聞き取れない》
What do I do? I can't understand him...
出てよ～｡
Answer the phone!
《ダメだ…やっぱり訓練中》
He isn't answering. He must be training...
(ユキ)フーちゃん？フーちゃん!?
Fu? Fu?
どこ行ったの!?
Where'd you go?
(ユキ)どこ!?どこ!?
Where are you? Where are you?
Fuuka! Fuuka!
風佳!?風佳～っ!?
My...
ﾏｲ ﾁｬｲﾙﾄﾞ ｲｽﾞ ﾐｯｼﾝｸﾞ｡
My child is missing!
Jeez...
あぁ～ん｡
絶対 ダメよ！
１人でウロチョロしないの！
Never do that again!
Don't run off by yourself!
はぁ～疲れた 頭痛い…｡
I'm exhausted...
And my head hurts.
Oh, now it's my turn...
(ユキ)あぁ…今度は 私が｡
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ケンジ)そっか 大変だったね｡
Wow, sounds like it's been rough.
なんか 私 ちょっと…
日本に帰りたくなってきた｡
I'm starting to want to return to Japan.
そ そんなこと言うなよ｡
D-Don't say that.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](ユキ)
だって どうせ ケンちゃん
ほとんど家にいないじゃない！
It isn't like you're ever at home!
ま まあ そうだけどさ
もうちょっと…｡
W-Well, I know...
Just wait a little longer.
いや まぁ…
３日後には帰るからさ｡
Anyway, I'll be home in three days.
それまで 何とか…｡
Until then, just...
《｢がんばってよ｣って言葉を➡
"Do your best" is a phrase I always have to stop myself from saying.
何度も言いそうになっては
飲む込む｡➡
子育てに対する｢がんばれ｣は
重荷にしかならない｡➡
When bringing up a child, those words add needless pressure.
ということに
僕も何度か失敗して気付いた》
After multiple failures, I realized this.
《仕事に対する｢がんばれ｣は
僕には励みになるんだけど…》
But when she tells me to do my best, I'm encouraged to work harder.
Daddy!
Do your best when you're training for the moon!
つきのくんれんがんばってね！
スーパンダマンで！
Like Supandaman!
スーパンダマンは
ムリしてがんばるんです！
Supandaman always does the best he can!
Supandaman?
《スーパンダマン？
また新たな…》
Another new character?
ありがと 風佳！
行ってくるよ～｡
Thanks, Fuuka!
Then, I'm off!
さすがに
もう｢カペー｣は言わないか｡
I guess she's grown out of saying "roo-ra."
ちょっと寂しいな…｡
でも それよりさ➡
It's a little sad.
True.
話し合えるってことの方が
実は もっと嬉しい｡
But the ability to communicate is much better.
《僕が宇宙飛行士になって➡
I wonder how they feel
２人は
どんな気持ちなんだろう｡➡
about my becoming an astronaut...
慣れ親しんだ日本を離れ➡
They've had to leave their native country,
親も友人もいない見知らぬ土地で
暮らすことになって➡
and live in an unfamiliar place, away from friends and relatives.
不安で仕方ないかな…｡➡
They must be scared.
やっぱり
日本に帰りたいかもな…》
They probably want to go back to Japan.
《僕が宇宙へ行くために➡
To send me to space,
彼女たちが払っている犠牲は
大きい》
they're sacrificing a lot.
《応えなきゃダメだな｡➡
I have to do my part.
And use the time and effort that would have otherwise gone to them...
一緒に過ごせなかった時間も
かけた苦労も…｡➡
帳消しには
できないだろうけど！》
It isn't enough to compensate their sacrifice...
パパが 月か…なんか不思議｡
Your daddy's going to the moon.
Isn't that incredible?
《僕が月へ行かなきゃ…
何の恩も返せない！》
...but I need to reach the moon before I can make things right!
現在
なぁ ケンジ
ｼﾞｮｲﾝﾄﾊﾟｰﾂは どこ行った？
Hey, Kenji... Where are the joint parts?
ああ こっちだよ ムッ君｡➡
Ah, they're over here, Mu.
形が何種類か あったから
それぞれ分けといたんだ｡
There are different types, so I was separating them.
おお～ さすがケンジ
ナイス判断！効率アップだよ！
Wow, you're always on top of things! Sharp thinking!
Now we're more efficient!
(ｱﾝﾃﾞｨ)言う必要はない｡
There's no need to tell them.
あいつらは仲良くやってる
ほっときゃいいだろ｡
They're working well together.
Let them be.
俺はな アンディ➡
Well, Andy...
ビンスさんの考えた方に
賛同してんだ｡➡
I have to agree with Vince.
危機感のない者には
成長もない｡➡
People only evolve when facing danger.
今のあいつらは
危機感を持つ必要がある｡
We have to keep them on their toes.
事実を知って
競合させれば➡
If they learn the truth and start to compete, they'll be more intense and focused.
必死になり
集中力も高まる｡➡
結果 それは
俺たちのチームに有益になる｡➡
That will benefit our team.
アンツに
この事実を告げるかどうかは➡
We were given the authority to decide whether to tell the Ants the truth.
俺たちの判断に託されたんだ｡➡
伝えることが
チームのプラスになるのなら➡
Assuming that the information will benefit the team...
言ってもいいとな｡
俺は奴らの様子を見て
言うべきだと判断した｡
After watching them work, I think we should tell them.
今すぐにでもな｡
The sooner the better.
コマンダーは お前なんだ
好きにしろ｡
You're the commander... Do as you like.
ケンジとムッタ
作業を 一時中断｡➡
Kenji, Mutta... I need you to stop working for a bit.
作戦会議だ
ガゼボに来てくれ｡
We're having a meeting.
Come to the gazebo.
ぷはぁ～いいな ここ｡
ハッハハ ホント｡
This is a nice place...
It is.
さて お前ら…｡
Okay, then...
ど どういうことですか？
Wh-What do you mean?
(ラブ)言葉の通りだ
最初から決まっていた｡
That's how it is.
It was decided before we began.
お前ら ２人のうち➡
Only one of you
月へ行けるのは
どちらか１人だけだ｡
can go to the moon.
そんな…｡
No way...
The hasty hare and the slow and steady turtle
Are both headed toward the place they call their goals
We forgot something very important once we grew up
Forget tomorrow, what can I do right now?
But the two of us
Have always remembered
The importance of taking off
The heavy shackles of hesitation
A brand new world
Is always waiting one step ahead of us
Even our failures will give us strength
And that will be the start of a new world
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#83 Kenji and I
Only one of us can go to the moon?
＜どちらか１人しか
月へ行けないなんて➡
Why?!
何でだよ？＞
(ケンジ)＜つまりは➡
That means we're no longer on the same side.
今までみたいに 二人三脚してちゃ
ダメってことだ＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Kenji and I"
(ケンジ)＜僕は こんなにも
薄情者だったのか＞
Am I really such a cruel person?